Guide to the Gates family papers 1888-1996
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Gates family papers
1888-1996
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0050gates
Gates family
3 linear feet.
The Gates family papers comprise articles and clippings, personal papers and photographs of a prominant Bellingham family. Collection materials were generated by businessman Cyrus and Mabel Huntoon Gates, and their children: Frances Ellen, Cyrus Kingsley, and Katherine Elizabeth.
A prominent Bellingham businessman and civic figure, Cyrus Gates moved from Vermont to Fairhaven, Washington in 1890 to work as private secretary for C.X. Larrabee. Gates became actively involved in various Larrabee business enterprises, holding part-ownership in the Roslyn-Cascade Coal Company, and serving as Secretary-Treasurer of the Pacific Realty Company until his death on January 13, 1927. Gates donated large amounts of time, money and land to civic and commercial development of the Fairhaven District and Chuckanut Drive. He was especially interested in the development of the city park system. Gates was survived by his wife Mabel Huntoon Gates and their three children: Frances Ellen, Cyrus Kingsley and Katherine Elizabeth. In 2004, the City of Bellingham purchased Woodstock Farm, the Gates’ family home along Chuckanut Bay, as a city park.
The Gates family papers comprise personal papers, photographs, and albums and scrapbooks spanning the period 1888-1996. Personal papers include articles and clippings, and papers generated by individual members of the Gates family. Cyrus Gates' papers include correspondence from Charles X. Larrabee encouraging his 1890 move from Vermont to Fairhaven, Washington. The collection also contains a small amount of material generated by Cyrus Gates’ wife, Mabel Huntoon Gates and their children: Frances Ellen, Cyrus “Cy” Kingsley, and Katherine “Betty” Elizabeth Gates. The bulk of the collection comprises photographs of the Gates family and friends, including images taken by Mabel Gates' brother, photographer Bert W. Huntoon, and images of Woodstock Farm, the Gates’ family home on Inspiration Point along Chuckanut Bay. There are also photograph albums and scrapbooks related to Mabel Huntoon Gates and her sister, Grace Huntoon Sheerer, as well as Cyrus Gates, which include photographs, personal papers, and news clippings.
The Gates family papers are organized in accordance with the following series arrangement:
Series I. Personal Papers, 1890-1977
Series II. Photographs, 1899-1991
Series III. Photograph Albums and Scrapbooks, 1888-1994
The collection is open to the public.
The Larrabee family papers at the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies include business correspondence generated by Cyrus Lester Gates through his work for C.X. Larrabee.
Collection formally donated by Barbara Sheerer Morris in 2017.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Gates, Cyrus --1858-1927.; Gates, Mabel Huntoon.; McCord, Frances Ellen Gates -- 1900-; Gates, Cyrus Kingsley -- 1905-1995.; Brooks, Katherine Elizabeth Gates.; Huntoon, Bert W. -- 1869-1947.
Gates family --Archives
Fairhaven (Bellingham, Wash.) -- History -- Sources.; Woodstock Farm (Bellingham, Wash.) -- History -- Sources -- Photographs.
Washington (State); Home and Family; Pioneers
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Personal Papers, 1890-1996; Series I
  Personal papers include correspondence from C.X. Larrabee to Cyrus Gates, encouraging his move from Vermont to Fairhaven, Washington in 1890. Cyrus Kingsley Gates' papers also include correspondence with Robert B. Thomas (author of Chuckanut Chronicles), Mary Bourque (daughter of C.X. Larrabee) and Consuelo Larrabee regarding local and family history.
  - Articles and Clippings re: Gates family, 1923; 1929; 1937; undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Cyrus Gates
    - C.X Larrabee correspondence, 1890 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Resolutions upon his death, 1927 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Obituaries, 1927 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Cyrus Kingsley Gates
    - Correspondence (Incoming), 1920-1990 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Correspondence (Outgoing), 1990-1991; undated (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Diary, 1918 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Diary (trip to Alaska), 1920 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Fairhaven High School Yearbook Aurora, 1919 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Fairhaven High School Memorabilia, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
    - First National Bank Checkbook, undated (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Fraternity membership card, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Letter announcing Cy’s death, 1996 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Oregon State Agricultural College degree certificate, 1928 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - St. John’s military academy - commencement program, 1923 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - St John’s military academy - rowing crew badge, undated (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Frances Ellen Gates (McCord)
    - Baby Book, 1900-1901 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Bellingham Public School – First Grade Report, 1907 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Correspondence (Incoming) re: Chuckanut Bay Property, 1977 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Marriage Service and certificate, 1923 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - Neale Bennett McCord (husband)- High School Yearbooks El Archivero, 1916; 1919 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Mabel Huntoon Gates
    - Correspondence (Incoming), 1900; 1927 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - Eldridge Family card and wedding invitation, 1920 (Box-folder 1/23)
    - Washington State Teaching Certificate, 1897 (Box-folder 1/24)
- Photographs, 1890-1991; Series II
  - Cyrus Gates, 1899; undated (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Cyrus Kingsley Gates, circa 1909-1929 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Cyrus Kingsley Gates, circa 1929-1991 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Cyrus Kingsley Gates, circa 1910s (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Frances Ellen Gates, circa 1920s (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Frances Ellen Gates, circa 1901- 1920s (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Katherine Elizabeth Gates, undated; 1936 (Box-folder 1/29)
  - Katherine Elizabeth Gates, circa 1936 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Mabel Huntoon Gates, circa 1890 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Mabel Huntoon Gates, 1898-1899; undated (Box-folder 1/30)
  - Gates Family Photographs, 1900-1929; undated (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Gates family friends, circa 1920s (Box-folder 1/32)
  - Unidentified people and places, undated (Box-folder 1/33)
  - Chuckanut Bay area, undated (Box-folder 1/34)
  - North Cascade and Mt. Baker region (Huntoon photos), 1923; 1925 (Box-folder 1/35)
  - Woodstock Farm, 1915-1917; 1923; 1935 (Box-folder 1/36)
- Photograph Albums and Scrapbooks, 1888-1994; Series III
  - Grace Huntoon / Mabel Huntoon Gates binder with photographs and miscellaneous documents, circa 1888-1920s (Box-folder 2/1)
    Assembled by Barbara Sheerer Morris and Tim Wahl.
  - Grace Huntoon Sheerer scrapbook with photographs and news clippings, circa 1890s-1907 (Box-folder 2/2)
    Includes items of interest to a young female student (the compiler) of the State Normal School in Bellingham and University of Washington. Photos of women's bicycling, sailing and picnic outings to Marietta and Chuckanut, etc. Social column clippings from newspapers.
  - "Around the Old Home Town" photograph album made for Betty Gates by Bert Huntoon, 1923 (Box-folder 2/3)
    Album contents include references to Woodstock as "Our Home..." reflecting the Huntoon's role as elders to their niece, Betty Gates Brooks Clark, after the death of her father.
  - Cyrus L. Gates binder with family photographs and miscellaneous documents, circa 1890-1994 (Box-folder 2/4)